2009年5月17日
May 17th, 2009.
对卑弥呼的进一步研究
Further research on Himiko.
卑弥呼是日本历史上第一位女王
According to legend, Himiko, the first queen of Japan,
传说她是一名利用邪术
was a powerful sorceress.
统治国家的强大术士
who ruled her empire through dark magic,
她手指一挥
spreading death and destruction.
就能带来毁灭和死亡
by the mere touch of her hand.
但她的野心被挫败
She was only stopped by a single twist of fate.
卑弥呼手下的将士起兵反叛
An army of her own generals bound and dragged Himiko.
他们把她带到凶险的
to an uninhabitable island.
恶魔海的一座孤岛上
in the middle of the treacherous Devil's Sea.
至今卑弥呼被埋葬在高山之下
There, she remains entombed beneath the mountains.
我在一张古老的地图上找到了蛛丝马迹
I found a speck on an old map that no one else has.
她在那里
And she's there,
等待着得到释放
waiting to be unleashed.
我必须第一个找到她
I have to get there first.
我最不愿意做的
Even if it means doing the last thing.
就是
I'd ever want to do…
扔下我的小劳拉
Leaving my Lara behind.
作出决定吧 劳拉
You gotta make decisions, Lara.
赶紧发力
You gotta make something happen.
抵挡攻击
Counter-punching doesn't work for you.
你必须更有技巧
You don't have the skill.
- 谢了 泰瑞 - 不客气
- Thanks, Terry. - You're welcome.
加油 劳拉
Come on, Lara!
别再跳舞 鼓起斗志
Stop dancing, start fighting.
来啊
Yes, girl!
来呀
Come on!
来吧 劳拉 你行的
Nice one, Lara! You've got this!
- 结束吧 - 还不能
- It's over. - Isn't!
到此为止
Then get out of it!
赶紧认输
Come on, Lara! Tap out.
不许再说
Don't say it.
你像条虫一样被吊打
You got whupped, girl. You got whupped.
- 哪有吊打 - 好吧 没有被吊打
- Not whupped. - Okay. Not whupped.
是被碾压
Marmalized.
碾压？她又不是什么超级英雄
"Marmalized"? She's not a freakin' superhero.
实际上是我让她的
Truth is, I let her…
不会记仇吧
We cool?
当然不会
Yeah, we're cool.
我玩的很开心
Was fun actually!
谢谢
Thanks.
下次我一定赢你
I'll get you next time.
看我碾压你
I'll marmalize you.
你今晚会早点回来的 对吧
You're home early tonight, right?
对
Yup.
回头见
Catch you later.
回见
Laters.
嘿 谁偷了我的苹果
Hey! Who stole my apple?
早该猜到是你
Should've known it was you.
我为什么要偷你的苹果
Why would I do a thing like that?
因为你自己买不起
'Cause you can't afford your own.
我看到记录 你拖欠会费了
Just seen you're behind with your payments.
泰瑞 我保证会补交会费的
Terry, look, I'll catch up on the payments, I promise.
我会还你的
I'll make it up to you.
找份工作吧 劳拉
Get a job, Lara.
你以为我穿成这样是为了搞笑吗
Do you think I'm dressed like this for fun?
劳拉 我真的很欣赏你 但是
I like you, Lara. I really do, but…
（不付钱 没得玩）
阿呼加太太 早上好
早上好 劳拉
- 嘿 - 嗨 你好吗
- Hey. - Hi.
- 很好 - 今天特别顺
- All good? - Yeah. Havin' a great day.
你呢
You?
- 挺好 - 是吗
- Yeah. - Yeah?
再问点别的 问她想不想去吃饭
Ask her more. Ask her for dinner or something. Do it.
快
Come on.
还有事吗
Anything else?
没有 没事啦
No, no, no.
再见 再见
搞什么 叫你问不问
What is your problem? Why didn't you ask her?
笨死了
Stupid boy.
猎狐赛安排好了吗 罗格
You got that fox hunt sorted, Rog?
差不多了
Yeah, more or less.
有30个「猎狗」报名了 现在就差「狐狸」了
Got 30 hounds signed up. Just gotta find a fox now.
不好找
Tough one, that.
得找个骑得快的 比赛才有意思
Need someone quick enough to make it interesting.
是啊 太慢就不好玩了
Yeah. No fun if they ain't quick.
又要傻傻的 以为自己能赢
But dumb enough to think they can win.
你们在打什么鬼主意
What are you two plotting?
我们要办场猎狐赛
We're gonna do a fox hunt.
- 什么赛 - 类似自行车赛
- A what? - Well, it's like a race.
当「狐狸」的车手先跑
Except the fox gets a head start,
一路上用油漆留下痕迹
leavin' a paint trail behind his bike.
让当「猎狗」的车手去追
For the baying hounds to follow.
如果油漆用完了
And if they haven't caught him.
猎狗却还没抓到狐狸
by the time the paint runs out…
奖金就全归狐狸
He wins all the money.
奖金有多少
How much money?
600块
600 quid.
你们要找的狐狸就在这儿
I think you just found yourself a fox.
你是来真的
Oh, you're bein' serious?
我是不够快 还是不够傻
Not quick or dumb enough for you?
没有 我的意思是
No, I mean, I just…
那就你了
You're on.
狐狸藏好 大家来找
"Hide fox, and all after!"
莎翁名句
Ooh, Shakespeare?
出自哈姆雷特 对吗
Hamlet, is it?
不知道 脑子里冒出来的
Don't know. Things just stick in my brain.
你读过哈姆雷特吗
You know it's Hamlet.
我再问你一次
And I ask you once again,
你为什么要当送外卖的
why on earth are you a bike courier?
因为你 布鲁斯
You, Bruce.
我想待在你身边
I wanna be close to you.
54321 出发
Five, four, three, two, one! Go!
借过
Excuse me!
走走走
Go, go, go!
她人呢 兄弟
Where is she, bro?
不会很久的 亲爱的
I won't be long, my love.
- 看着点路 - 你才该看着点后视镜
- Oi! Watch where you're going! - Use your mirrors!
走
Go! Go!
没想到会在这儿见你
Fancy seeing you here.
安娜
Ana.
你不用特地过来
You didn't have to come.
我已经不需要监护人了
I don't need a guardian anymore.
你确定吗
Really?
你在干油漆活吗
Have you been decorating?
我很久没见你了
Haven't seen you for a long time.
你就没见过真正的我
You've never seen me.
对不起
I'm sorry.
谢谢你过来
Thanks for coming.
今天是怎么回事
What was today about?
我需要那笔奖金
I needed the money.
不 你不需要
No, you don't. There's an inheritance.
有一大笔遗产等着你去继承 只要你愿意
waiting for you if only you would step…
我不愿意
I won't.
已经过去七年了 劳拉
It's been seven years, Lara.
东京警方五年前就已经
Tokyo police stopped looking for your father.
放弃搜寻你爸爸了
five years ago.
连私家侦探都不肯再接我们的委托了
Private investigators won't even take our money anymore.
我知道 这很难接受
I know it's difficult to accept.
但你真的必须来把那些文件签了
But you really must come in and sign those papers now.
你就是为此而来的吧
Hmm. That's why you came.
不 我是为你而来的
No. I came for you.
想想你能为这个世界做多少贡献
Just think what you can do for the world,
凭你的能力 凭你的财富
with your potential, with your wealth.
是他的财富不是我的
His wealth. Not mine.
我这么跟你说吧
Listen, it's very simple…
如果你不签署那些文件
If you don't sign the papers,
你爸爸奋斗一生的成果都会被拍卖掉
then everything your father worked for will be sold off.
不只是他的公司
Not just the company,
还有克劳馥庄园
but Croft Manor, also.
他要知道你把庄园弄丢了 他会怎么想
Can you imagine how he would feel if you lost the house?
劳拉 你爸爸已经不在了
Lara, your father's gone.
但你可以接受他未竟的事业
But you can pick up where he left off.
这是血脉相承的
It's in your blood.
对不起
I'm sorry.
我不是那克劳馥的一类人
I'm just not that kind of Croft.
我不想你走 爸爸
But I don't want you to go, Daddy.
我不会去很久的
I won't be long, my love.
你一定要明白
You must understand.
我们克劳馥家族肩负重任 还有使命需要完成
We Crofts, we have responsibilities, jobs to do.
我会想你的
But I'll miss you.
我知道 我也会想你的
I know. I'll miss you, too.
我有一个解决办法
But I may have a solution to that.
看见这个没
See this?
这是你妈妈的 它拥有特殊的力量
This was your mother's, so it has special powers.
是什么意思
What do you mean?
当你想见某个人时
Ever you want to feel close to someone,
就把它紧紧握在手里
just put it in your hand, and you hold it tightly.
在心里想着那个人 对方就会感应到
And you think of that person, and they'll know.
- 真的吗 - 真的
- Really? - Yeah.
它有魔力 有了这个
It's magic.
不管我去了哪里
And it means that we'll always be together,
我们都能心灵相通
wherever I am.
好不好
Okay?
爸爸一转眼就回来了
I'll be back before you know I'm gone.
（克劳馥集团）
喂
Oi!
送外卖走后门
Couriers round the back.
我不是送外卖的
Uh, I'm not a courier.
好吧 我是
Well, I am.
没错 所以走后门
Right. So round the back.
我是来见安娜·米勒的
I'm here to see Ana Miller.
好吧 你得和别人一样先登记
Well, you gotta sign in like everyone else.
叫什么
What's your name?
劳拉
Lara.
克劳馥
Croft.
需要签名的那几页已经标注出来了
The pages that require a signature.
方便您翻阅
are marked for your convenience.
（因失踪宣告死亡）
要不要让亚夫先生
Would you like Mr. Yaffe.
为你解释一下细节
to take you through the particulars?
我想我这一签
I gather I sign.
就意味着爸爸彻底死了
and Dad is dead.
我知道这对你来说有多难
I can imagine how difficult this is for you.
我也很想他
I miss him, too.
（在此处签字）
那个是我爸爸的
That was Dad's.
是的 克劳馥小姐 根据理查德的遗嘱
Yes, Miss Croft. According to Richard's will,
在他过世之后
in the event of his death.
我要把这个转交给你
I was to give it to you.
机关盒 一种日本的解密游戏
Karakuri. Japanese puzzle.
严格意义上来说
Um, technically speaking,
您必须先在文件上签字
you're meant to sign the papers first.
真不懂你爸爸
I could never understand.
为什么对这些东西那么着迷
your father's obsession with those things.
你不会相信
Wouldn't believe how many of these.
家里还有多少这样的玩意儿
were lying around the house.
这背后肯定有什么玄机
There was gonna be some purpose to it.
来自我人生终点的第一封信
"The first letter from my final destination."
可是他并没有留下什么信件
But he didn't leave a letter.
（来自我人生终点的第一封信）
- 抱歉 失陪一下 - 劳拉 我…
- If you'll excuse me. - Lara, I…
（纪念理查德·克劳馥）
我人生的终点
"My final destination."
第一个字母
The first letter.
（俄罗斯 伊万诺夫·亚历山大）
（中国 詹姆斯·冯）
（美国 约翰逊·斯图尔特）
爸爸 你到底要做什么
Dad, what were you up to?
（看我）
你好 小不点
Hello, sprout.
我就知道你能解开我的谜题
I knew I could trust you to solve my puzzle.
很不幸 如果你正在看着带子的话
Unfortunately, if you're watching this tape,
那意味着我已经死了
then, uh, it means that I must be dead.
现在你应该知道了
It'll be obvious to you by now.
我的人生
that there was more to my life.
不仅仅只有董事会和生意
than just boardrooms and business deals.
有些事之前没法告诉你
Things that I couldn't tell you about before.
你妈妈去世的时候 我悲痛欲绝
When your mother died, grief nearly destroyed me.
我开始四处搜寻 渴望找到
I began searching the world,
另一个世界的痕迹
desperate for a hint of another realm,
证明超自然现象是存在的
for proof that the supernatural is real.
好让我感觉你妈妈还在
Anything to feel her with me again.
我对此产生了极大的兴趣
I made quite a hobby of it, sprout.
现在
Now…
我需要你帮我一个忙
I need you to do me a favor.
我要你 把我所有关卑弥呼的研究
I need you to burn all my research.
全部烧掉
on the Himiko project.
把我的笔记本
Just burn all of it.
录像带通通烧掉
The notebooks, the tapes, everything.
事关重大
It's very important.
如果落入坏人手里
If it falls into the wrong hands,
会引发大灾难
then it could be catastrophic,
所以求你了 一定要全部烧掉
so please do it straightaway.
我知道你不喜欢听别人指挥
I know you hate being told what to do,
可求你了 一定要答应我
but please promise me that.
真希望你永远不会看到这卷带子
I hope you never have to see this tape.
但如果你看到了
But if you do,
你发现了我用生命守护的事业
you've found my secret calling.
希望你也能找到你的
I hope you find yours.
爸爸爱你
Dad loves you.
卑弥呼
"Himiko."
10月5日
October 5th.
他们叫卑弥呼为「死神之母」
They called Queen Himiko the "Mother of Death."
关于她的所有故事
All the stories about her.
结局都是血流成河
end in rivers running red with blood.
她蛊惑人心 控制人的意念
Bewitching people, controlling minds,
她只需用手轻轻一碰
spreading death and destruction.
便可散布死亡与毁灭
with just the touch of her hand.
直到她手下的将军把他活埋在坟墓里
The bloodshed only ended.
杀戮才得以终止
when her own generals buried her alive in a tomb,
他们把她埋在一个与世隔绝的小岛上
sealing her away from the outside world,
从此不见天日
on an island no one could reach.
历史上没有留下坟墓存在的证据
History's all but erased its existence.
遗落的邪马台岛
The lost island of Yamatai.
我肯定就是这个地方
I'm certain this is the place.
2011年7月29日
July 29th, 2011.
总算有个船长
I finally found a captain.
肯带我去那座小岛
willing to take me to the island.
我必须第一个找到她
I must get there first to ensure her powers.
确保她的强大力量不会落入坏人手里
will never fall into the wrong hands.
（理查德 价钱是两万美元）
（陆仁 香港阿伯丁）
（典当行）
这个护身符是日本昭和天皇
That amulet was given to my father.
送给我父亲的
by Emperor Showa of Japan.
是吗
Right. Right. Well…
不过这个玩意不是日本的
This ain't from Japan.
你说对了
You're correct.
昭和天皇是从古代马拉塔国王
Emperor Showa was given it by the grandson.
的孙子那儿得到的
of the former emperor of Maratha.
马拉塔 你在开玩笑吗
"Maratha"? You're having a laugh, in't ya?
这位王孙又是
And he, himself, got it from Thibaw,
从缅甸的末代国王
the last king of Burma.
被流放到印度的锡袍王那儿得到的
when he was exiled in India.
被流放到印度
"Exiled in India."
故事很精彩
What a fascinating tale.
你说的这些都有
And you got all this, uh, provenance.
材料证明出处吧
down on paper, do ya?
要是有证明材料
If I had the provenance on paper,
我就拿去克里斯蒂拍卖行了
I'd be at Christie's, wouldn't I?
但
But, um…
今天你撞大运了
This is your lucky day.
- 是吗 - 对
- Is it? - Yeah.
艾伦 我警告过你
Alan! What have I told you.
不许跟客人调情
about flirting with the customers?
我没在调情 这是我自然流露的魅力
I'm not flirting. I'm just naturally charismatic.
我没在调情 别见怪 我没在调情
I was not flirting. I'm sorry.
我是在调情
I was flirting.
你来看看
Have a look.
亮出笑容 亲和随意
Big smiles, nice and casual.
好的
Right, well, I'm pleased to say.
我们愿意收购你这件东西
we're in a position to make you an offer.
一万
Ten.
拜托
Please?
再加一点
Just a tad bit more.
这是我爸爸留给我的唯一念想
That's all I have to remember my dad by.
你爸爸死了 太不幸了
Oh. Oh, your dad died.
姑娘家年纪轻轻就没了爸爸
That's a shame. It's a terrible thing.
真可怜
for a young woman to lose her father.
好吧 看在这份上
Really. All right. Fair enough.
9000英镑
9, 000.
你刚才说是一万
You just said 10.
来这演死老爸苦情戏的人多了去了
Well, people come in here trying the dead dad shit all the time.
你每次都信以为真 艾伦
And you fall for it all the time.
- 我哪有每次都信以为真 - 不 你就是有
- I don't fall for it all the time. - Yes, you do.
我就被骗了两次
Last week, you fell for it twice.
上个星期你就会骗了两次
I fell for it twice.
我没骗你
It's the truth.
好吧 我很乐意继续讨价还价
Fine. I'm happy to keep negotiating.
现在是8000了
Because now the price is eight.
- 好吧 你赢了 - 这不就结了
- Okay. You win. - Ah, finally.
我打心眼里感谢你
Thank you. Really.Thank you.
这就是为你这种人准备的
For just such occasions.
她烫到我的蛋蛋了
You burnt me taters!
收敛点吧 艾伦 太不像话了
Sort yourself out, Alan. Seriously.
里面是热咖啡
That is hot coffee.
（香港）
不好意思 你们会说英语吗
Excuse me, do you speak English?
对不起 不会
Sorry, no.
不会吗 谢谢
No? Thank you.
不好意思
Sorry. Excuse me.
请问你认识一个叫陆仁的人吗
Do you know a Lu Ren? Lu Ren?
陆仁 一点也没听说过吗
Not even a tiny bit?
- 不好意思 你会说英语吗 - 小姐
- Do you speak English? - Lady.
需要帮忙吗
You need help?
是的 需要
Yes. I do.
我在找一个叫陆仁的人
I'm looking for this guy called Lu Ren.
应该是在…
Um, he's supposed to…
- 陆仁的船 - 是的
- Lu Ren boat. - Yes.
忍耐号 就在那儿
Endurance. Over there.
忍耐号是哪条船
"Endurance"? Which one?
站住
Wait!
别过来
Stay back.
把包还给我
Gimme the bag.
你们的小费就别想要了
You just lost your tip.
你的舌头别想要了
You just lose your tongue.
陆仁
Lu! Lu Ren!
救命
Help! Help!
你死定了
从我船上滚下去 快滚
快走 他又喝高了
Run! Run! He's drunk again!
这就对了
谢谢
Thank you.
你是什么人
什么
What?
我问你在我船上干什么
I said what are you doing on my boat?
我跟他们不是一起的
I'm not with them.
我在找陆仁
I'm looking for a man named Lu Ren.
恭喜你找到我了 现在滚吧
Congratulations, you found me. Now get lost.
请等一下 先听我说几句
Please. Wait. Just listen. I need…
好了 快点走
Okay, let's go.
我不是来找麻烦的
I'm not here to make any trouble.
脚别停
Keep walking.
能不能请你先把枪放下
Could you please put that gun down and just…
活见鬼了
Oh, for God's sake.
我的父亲理查德·克劳馥在你这儿买过一艘船
My father, Richard Croft, tried to buy a boat from you.
他没有在我这买过
No. No. Not me, he didn't.
他买过
Yes, he did.
你叫陆仁
Your name is Lu Ren.
这是你的字据
This is from you.
谢谢 我知道自己叫什么
Yes, I know my name, thanks.
我跟我爸爸同名 这是他写的 不是我
It's the same as my father's, and he wrote that, not me.
那我找他有事
Well, then I need to talk to him.
除了你 他还有一大堆债主
You and 100 other people he owed money…
- 他在哪里 - 我不知道！
- Where is he? - I don't know, okay?
有一天他开着船就走了
One day, he just left on his boat,
我再也没有见过他
and I never saw him again, all right?
那是七年前的事吗
Was this seven years ago?
我知道我们两个爸爸去哪里了
I think I know where they went. Our dads.
去冰冷的海底了吗
To the bottom of the sea?
他们是去找一座无人岛
They were headed to an uninhabited island.
在日本沿海海域
Somewhere off the coast of Japan.
过去叫邪马台岛
It used to be called Yamatai.
我要到那去
I'm gonna go there and find out.
弄清楚他们出了什么事
what happened to them.
祝你好运
Good luck. There's at least.
日本沿海至少有6000座岛屿
6, 000 islands off the coast of Japan,
基本都是无人岛
and hardly any of them are populated.
不要紧 我有地图
Well, I have a map.
我只要搞清楚这些是什么意思
Now, all I need to do is to figure out what these are.
我认为这是岛屿所在地的坐标
I think these are coordinates.
是钟表指针
They're clock hands.
不是钟表指针
They're not clock hands.
怎么可能是钟表指针呢
Definitely not clock hands. They're…
还真是钟表指针
They are clock hands.
三
Three…
就是这个
That's the one.
它在恶魔海的正中央
That's right in the middle of the Devil's Sea.
你不如在脚上绑块石头
You might as well tie a stone to your foot.
直接跳海来得痛快
and jump off the boat now.
这是一场冒险之旅
It'll be an adventure.
送死可不叫冒险之旅
Death is not an adventure.
你不想知道他们的下落吗
Don't you want to know what happened to them?
那对我来说已经不重要了
I just don't care anymore, okay?
我忙得很 有很多事要做
Look, I'm a busy guy. I got stuff to do.
你昨晚输了多少钱
How much did you lose last night?
你凭什么认为我输了
What makes you think I lost?
因为你看起来像在借酒消愁
Well, it looked like you were.
不像在庆祝
drowning your sorrows, not celebrating.
送我去邪马台 这钱就归你
Yours if you help me get to Yamatai.
好让我拿去买棺材吗
And what will I spend it on, a coffin?
那我就拿这笔钱
Then I'll go and get myself.
去自己买两条你这种破船
two rust buckets like this with that.
就算你有一条船 或者两条
Even if you had a boat, or two,
没等你开出港口 船就沉了
you'd sink 'em before you even left the harbor.
你需要一个经验丰富的船长
What you need is an experienced captain.
你另外一只鞋里藏了什么 宝贝
So, what's in the other shoe?
6月23日
June 23rd.
我可能又找到了一条线索
I may have found the next piece to the puzzle.
这些古画指向墓穴的位置
Ancient drawings hint to the location of the tomb.
一扇设计精妙的大门将她与世隔绝
and an elaborate door to keep her contained.
我找到了破译密码的方法
I've found a way to decipher the codes.
我一定能够找到她
I'm sure I can get to her.
根据古代编年史记载
The ancient Nihongi chronicles state.
进入墓穴的人
that within the tomb,
必须面对卑弥呼的严峻考验
one must face the "Ordeals of Himiko."
跨越灵魂的鸿沟
Cross the Chasm of Souls,
祈祷在卑弥呼的八张面具下幸存
pray to survive the faces of Himiko,
见证由她的千名侍女组成的大军
behold her army of a thousand handmaidens,
降临在卑弥呼最后的安息之地
descend upon Himiko's final resting place,
释放她的灾祸
unleashing her scourge.
7月6日
July 6th. I'm convinced.
我确定有人在监视我的行动
that my progress is being monitored.
现在我知道他们是谁了
I know them by name now…
圣三一秘社
The Order of Trinity.
他们是一个好战的古老组织
An ancient militant organization.
寻求操纵自然力量的方法
that seeks control over the supernatural.
从而统治全人类
to rule the fate of mankind.
如果卑弥呼就是
What if Himiko is the weapon.
圣三一想要寻找的武器呢
that Trinity has been seeking?
睡不着吗
Can't sleep?
景色真美
It's beautiful.
趁现在多看几眼
Enjoy it while you can.
之后就要进入香港和加州之间
We're headed into the most dangerous stretch of water.
最危险的海域了
between Hong Kong and California.
你爸爸真会挑度假的地方
Your dad sure knew how to pick a holiday.
是啊 显然他就喜欢干出人意料的事
Yeah. He had a knack for the unexpected. Apparently.
不过我开始怀疑 他是不是疯了
I am starting to wonder if he'd gone mad, though.
他好像分不清虚实真假
He didn't seem to know what was real and what wasn't,
沉迷于一个古代日本的死亡女王
obsessing over some ancient Japanese death queen.
有的男人就是喜欢危险的女人
Hey, some men like dangerous women.
有的男人真的很蠢
Some men are foolish.
什么
What?
晚安 陆仁 做个好梦
Good night, Lu Ren. Sweet dreams.
离神射手威廉·泰尔还有一步之遥
Not William Tell yet, but you're close.
威廉·泰尔只是传说 爸爸
William Tell was a myth, Dad.
每个传说都有一定的现实基础
Well, all myths have foundation in reality.
我要出远门了 小不点
I have to head off, sprout.
可是你才刚刚回来
But you've only just come back.
- 爸爸一转眼就回来了 - 我甚至不知道你都走了
- I'll be back before… - I even know you're gone.
安娜会照顾你的
Ana will keep an eye on you.
我不需要你派员工来给我当保姆
I don't need one of your employees babysitting me.
我自己能照顾自己
I can take care of myself.
乖女儿
My girl.
劳拉
Lara.
永远不要忘记爸爸爱你
Never forget Dad loves you.
我知道
I know.
我就知道会吵醒你
Thought that might wake you.
你的岛就在前面
Your island's found us.
邪马台
Yamatai.
船只失控了
We've lost all control!
- 我们得弃船了 - 什么
- We need to abandon ship. - What?
在这儿只有死路一条
We're dead in the water.
船支持不了多久了
It's not gonna hold much longer.
我们必须马上离开
We need to get off this boat now.
等等
Wait!
我爸的笔记
Dad's papers!
别拿了 劳拉
Forget them! Lara!
劳拉 快走
Lara. Come on!
陆仁
Lu!
救生船
The lifeboat!
小心
Watch out!
陆仁
Lu!
我在哪里
Where am I?
终于醒了
Ah! She's awake.
一开始我还很担心你
I was beginning to get worried about you.
是因为礁石
A reef.
你撞了上去
You hit it.
幸亏我发现了你
Thank God I found you.
想来这里的人都死在了激流之下
Most people who try to come here die in the currents.
几乎不可能活着到这儿
Almost impossible to get here.
更别提回去了
Even harder to leave.
我的包呢
Where's my…
在这里
Right here.
你来这里干什么 劳拉
What are you doing here, Lara?
我有两个女儿
I have two daughters.
发色和你一样
Dark hair like you.
像你一样漂亮
Pretty like you.
抱歉 忘了自我介绍
Forgive me. Rude.
这里很久没来客人了
I haven't hosted a guest here in a very long time.
我叫马赛厄斯·沃格尔
My name is Mathias Vogel.
你一定饿了吧
You must be hungry.
我以前常常在想
You know, I used to imagine.
在这些罐头里
that I might find an ear.
我迟早会吃到一只耳朵
inside one of those cans eventually.
是不是很疯狂
Isn't that mad?
在这岛上过了那么久
I guess being on this island for so long.
不发疯才怪呢
can make you a little crazy.
唯一能说话的对象是
The only person that I get to talk to.
电话另一端的那些家伙
is on the other end of this phone.
但他们总是重复一句话
And they always say the same thing…
在我的工作完成前我不能回家
I can't go home until my work on the island is done.
你的工作是什么
What kind of work do you do?
各种各样的事 一切听我老板的
Oh, a mix of things. At the mercy of my employer.
在找这个吗
You looking for this?
命运的女神总是会给我惊喜
The machinations of fate never cease to amaze me.
通往卑弥呼的大门
"The door to Himiko."
理查德找到了入口
Richard had the entrance.
得来全不费工夫
All that wasted time.
你把这个世界上
You have brought me the thing.
我最想要的东西带给了我
that I most wanted in this world.
谢谢
Thank you.
你知道我爸爸多少事情
What do you know about my father?
你们父女俩很像
Now I see the likeness.
都很聪明 长得也像
The intelligence in the face.
同样的不计后果
The recklessness.
其实合作一点就没事了
All he had to do was cooperate.
可是理查德他拒绝了
Of course, being Richard, he refused.
还以为自己在拯救世界
Thought he was saving the world.
他在哪里
Where is he?
他在哪儿
在天上 我杀了他
He's with God now. I killed him.
真是抱歉 我刚才太直接了
I'm sorry if I was too blunt. I'm out of practice.
已经七年了
It's been seven years.
七年了
Seven years.
快点
Come on.
Come on, come on!
到下面去
Come on. Get down there.
（巴特纳）
用推车来推
Get those skids moving!
快走
Move.
Move!
排好队
Let's go!
捡起来
Pick it up!
快点 走 往前走
Come on, go!
绑起来
Tie her up!
好了 可以了
Okay, winch it up!
赶紧干活
Back to work.
劳拉·克劳馥
Lara Croft.
你不该来这儿的
You shouldn't have come here.
但很高兴你来了
But I'm glad that you did.
收拾一下 我们转移
Pack it up. We're moving camp!
- 好了 把东西都收拾好 - 快走
- All right, let's pack it up! - Okay, move out!
收拾好 马上就走
We're moving camp!
动作快点 你 快走
Keep it moving! You, move!
快点儿
Move it, move it.
动起来 快点 我们走
Pick it up! Come on, let's go!
他们都是什么人
Who are these people?
有的是遇到海难的渔夫 我们走
Some are shipwrecked fishermen.
有的给了人贩子钱 想偷渡
And some paid smugglers to take 'em to a better life.
结果却被带到了这里
Instead, they brought 'em here.
快点 都给我动作快点
Come on! We're backed up here. Move!
他说他杀了我父亲
He said he killed my dad.
还有我父亲
He killed mine.
他们看见的
They saw it.
被他残忍的杀害了
Cold-blooded murder.
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
我不该把你带到这里来
I'm sorry that I brought you here.
你确实利用了一个宿醉的水手
Well, you did take advantage of a drunken sailor.
快点 快走
Come on, move!
至少我们还没死
At least we're not dead yet.
死不了
No shit.
我这里需要几个架子
I need some CL 20 up here!
好了 动作快
Come on, let's go!
没事吧
You okay?
让他赶紧起来继续干活
Get him up and back to work right now.
等等
Hang on.
- 趁现在 - 让他休息 我们替他干
- Right now! - Let him rest. We'll manage.
让他赶紧起来干活
Get him back to work right now!
他生病了 伙计 需要休息
He's sick, man. He needs to rest.
全都回去干活
Get back to work!
听到没有 全都回去干活
You heard him! Let's get back to work!
劳拉
Hey, Lara.
劳拉 准备好
Lara! Get ready.
快跑
Go!
小心
Look out!
快追 动作快
Let's spread out! Spread out!
抓住她
Get her!
快
Get a move on!
抓住她
Grab her!
她掉进河里了 要我们去追吗
She's in the river. You want us to follow?
不用
No.
我派火箭去找她
I'm sending Rocket to track her.
她要是没死 火箭会抓他回来
If she survives, he'll bring her back.
不是吧
Really?
别乱动 乖乖跟我回营地
Easy now, easy. I'm taking you back to camp.
别再挣扎了
Stop struggling!
等等
Wait!
等一下
No, no, no, no!
不是她
I'm not mad. I'm not mad, I'm not mad.
别去看
Just ignore it. It'll go away.
爸爸
Dad?
是我
It's me.
爸爸
Dad?
不是劳拉 你走开 像往常一样
It's not real. Ignore it. It'll go away. It always does.
看着我
No, look at me, look at me.
拜托
Please.
这你还记得吗
Do you remember this? Do you remember:
求你
We used to…
是我啊
It's me.
我是劳拉
It's Lara.
惊喜啊
Sprout.
天那 真的是你
What the blazes are you doing here?
我严重受伤了
Dad, I'm hurt.
别担心
It's all right.
我比你更受伤
This will hurt me more than it hurts you.
你说什么
What?
好吧
All right.
你会好好的
You're all right. You're all right.
好了
All right. It's all right.
天黑了
It's done.
休息吧
Rest now.
守着我
Will you stay with me?
我哪儿也不去
I'm not going anywhere.
我们找到了
Vogel! We found it! Yeah!
Yeah! Come on! We found it!
我找到了
I found it.
派运输机来
Send the transport.
我以为你走了
I thought you'd gone.
通常在岛上见到你
Usually when I see you on this island,
不知所踪的是你
it's you who disappears.
给我吧
Let me do that.
过来
Come here.
你后来去了哪里
So, sprout, where did you end up?
牛津还是剑桥
Did you go to Oxford or Cambridge?
告诉我 是哪个
Come on, which was it?
知道吗 爸爸 我…
You know what, Dad?
没上大学
I didn't go to university.
没事 还有时间 你年纪还小
Well, there's time yet. You're still only a child.
不 你当年离开我的时候 我年纪还小
No, I was a child when you left me.
轻一点
Ah, careful.
我一生最艰难的时刻
Hardest day of my life.
就是放弃回到你身边的那一刻
when I gave up trying to get back to you.
我意识到她永远不会放我走
But I realized she'd never let me leave.
你在说些什么 她是谁
What are you talking about? Who's "she"?
卑弥呼
Himiko.
圣三一派沃格尔来找她的坟墓
Trinity had sent Vogel to find her tomb.
弄醒她以获取她的力量
so that he could wake her and get her power.
我必须阻止他们
I had to stop them.
那就对了
Right.
没有我 沃格尔找不到坟墓的
Vogel can't find the tomb without me.
但既然我死了…
And since I'm dead.
我剩下的研究也全都被你烧了
and since you've burnt the rest of my research,
他这辈子都找不到
he'll never find it.
那个
So…
关于这一点
About that.
让你烧了我的研究
What part of "burn all my papers"…
你哪个字听不懂啊
did you not understand?
如果我烧了它们 我就找不到你了
If I'd burned the papers, I wouldn't have found you.
我到时候设置干扰和虚假线索
I set diversions and false leads wherever I could.
这么多年 我想尽办法误导他们
I watched for years as they got it wrong.
现在你却亲手给他们指了路
And now you lead them by the hand.
不就是让一个手里有枪的精神病人 找到了某个遗迹吗
So a gun-toting psychopath finds some ancient remains.
有什么大不了的
So what?
如果沃格尔打开了坟墓
If Vogel opens that tomb,
卑弥呼的诅咒就会被释放
Himiko's curse will be unleashed on the world.
爸爸 你听我说
Dad, listen…
你来这里就是个错误
You coming here was a mistake.
我来这里 是为了弄清楚你发生了什么
I came here to find out what happened to you.
只要坟墓是安全的
So long as the tomb was safe,
你就会安全
you were safe.
我在努力保护你的安全
I was trying to keep you safe.
可我却低估了你的…
But I underestimated your…
我的什么
My what?
- 愚蠢吗 - 不
- Stupidity? - No.
你的勇敢
Your bravery.
我们得离开岛
We have to get off this island.
根本没办法离开 劳拉
There's no way off, Lara.
沃格尔有一部卫星电话
Vogel's got a satellite phone.
可以拿过来 找人来救我们
We can get to it. We can call for help.
沃格尔有一支军队
Vogel has an army.
是你教我永远不要放弃
You were the one who taught me to never give up.
今时不同往日
That was a different time.
我也不是当年的我了
When I was a different man.
- 劳拉 - 但我还是当年那个人的女儿
- Lara. - Well, I'm still his daughter.
劳拉
Lara!
走吧
Come on!
换个组合试一试
Try another combination.
不行再换
And another one, and another one.
拜托 拜托 告诉我密码
Come on. Come on, give me the damn code.
（运输机已出发）
再用炸药试试
Hey. We're trying the explosives again.
去放炸药
Set another charge.
是 老大
Yes, boss.
装炸药 别说话了
Get over there. Stop talking.
拿上枪 我去拿卫星电话
Get the guns. I'm gonna get the sat phone.
然后我们想办法一起离开
Then we'll find a way for all of us to get out of here.
现在就走 赶快带他们走
We need to leave now.
沃格尔
Vogel! They re escaping!
走
Go!
射他们
Shoot them!
- 带他们去安全的地方 - 好
- Get them to safety. - Okay.
我会跟上的 快走
I'll be right behind you. Go.
见鬼
Shit.
我们得走了
We have to move.
我等在这里
I have to wait here.
我不会丢下劳拉不管的
I'm not leaving Lara behind.
很美吧 理查德
It's beautiful, isn't it, Richard?
真希望早点知道你还活着
I wish I would've known that you were alive all these years.
至少还能有个人陪我说说话
At least I would've had somebody to talk to.
我需要你的帮助 理查德
I need your help, Richard.
帮我把大门打开
Get the door open for me.
都已经七年了
It's been seven years.
我要回家去见家人
I'm going home to see my family.
如果我开启了坟墓 你就没有家人了
If I open that tomb, you won't have a family.
打开
Open it!
休想
Never!
随你便吧
Have it your way.
你帮或不帮 我早晚都会进去的
With or without you, I'm getting inside that tomb.
把枪放下
Put that down!
放下枪
Put it down.
你觉得弓箭会比枪快吗
You don't think I can pull this trigger before you hit me with that arrow.
杀了他 劳拉 动手
Shoot him, Lara. Shoot him!
行了 把武器放下
Come on, put your weapon down.
动手 劳拉 不能让他找到卑弥呼
Shoot him, Lara. We can't let him get to Himiko.
你该不会信他胡说吧
You really don't believe this nonsense, do you?
让你爸爸开门 不然他就得死
Tell your father to open the door, or he's dead.
你能说服他的 劳拉
You can make him do it, Lara.
运输机已经上路了
Transport's already on its way.
我们可以一起离开这座该死的岛
We can all be off this goddamn island.
让他杀了我
Let him shoot me.
牺牲我一个能拯救成千上万的人
Sacrificing one life is worth saving millions.
你自己选吧
It's your decision.
扣动扳机的是你的手
It's your finger that's pulling this trigger.
- 对不起 - 不
- I'm sorry. - No.
我来这里 不是为了看你被杀
I haven't come all this way to see you die.
让我来
I'll do it.
我来帮你开
I'll open it.
克劳馥家里总算有个理智的人
Finally, a Croft with some sense.
女士优先
Ladies first.
留好路标
Mark the path.
她还有气息
She's still breathing.
也可能是由气压差产生的风
Or it's a change in atmospheric pressure.
继续前进
Keep walking.
看你脸上的表情
You should've seen the look on your…
在机关不是防止外来的人
That wasn't designed to keep people out.
而是为了阻止里面的人出去
That was put there to keep people in.
爸爸
Dad?
灵魂的鸿沟
Chasm of Souls.
接下来是你
You go next.
祈祷在卑弥呼的八张面具下幸存
"Pray to survive the faces of Himiko."
离得越来越近了
We're getting closer.
死亡女王令白昼变成了黑夜
"The Death Queen turns day to night.
唯有她死亡 方能起死回生
"She must die to bring back life."
该死
Oh, shit.
- 小心地面 - 劳拉
- The floor! - Lara!
肯定有办法让机关停下
There's gotta be a way to stop this.
四处找一找
Look around!
赶快找找
Come on. Come on!
沃格尔 你们那里怎么样了
Vogel, what's going on?
祈祷幸存
"Pray to survive."
这个钥匙孔 需要一把钥匙
It's a keyhole. We need a key!
祈祷是指转经筒
The prayer wheels!
劳拉
Lara!
不起作用
It's not working.
看看其他几个转经筒
Check the other prayer wheels.
试试这个
Try this!
不行
No.
等等
Wait.
这是颜色谜题
It's a color puzzle.
死亡女王令白昼变成了黑夜
"The Death Queen turns the day to night."
- 黑色 - 黑色 给
- Black. - Black! Here!
见鬼
Shit!
蓝色
Blue!
不对
No!
接着
Here!
不起作用
It doesn't work.
劳拉
Lara!
这是最后一个 黄色
Last one! Yellow!
还是不行
It's not working.
全部试一下
Just try them all, damn it!
死亡女王令白昼变成了
"The Death Queen turns the day to night."
唯有她死亡 方能起死回生
"She must die to bring back… Life."
快啊
Come on!
生命的颜色
The color of life.
我脚下快没地方了
I'm running out of floor!
绿色
Green!
我们家就数你最聪明 小不点
You always were the brains of the family, sprout.
继续前进吧 小不点
Well, let's get going, sprout.
地面呢
Where's the floor?
没了
Gone.
照明弹
Flare.
快来 劳拉
Come on, Lara.
我回去找她
I'm going back for her.
我跟你一起去
I'm coming with you.
你爸爸是为我们牺牲的
You dad gave his life for us.
由卑弥呼的一千名侍女组成的军队
Himiko's army of a thousand handmaidens.
这些侍女是为了给卑弥呼殉葬而自尽
They sacrificed themselves in ritual suicide.
死后继续侍奉她们的女王
to serve their queen in the afterlife.
跟你笔记里写的一样
Exactly as your notes.
找到她了
We found her.
胜利就在眼前 赶紧把事办完
All right, this is it. We're finishing this.
现在回头还来得及
It's not too late to change your mind.
传说和现实是两码事 理查德
There's a very big difference between myth and reality, Richard.
你的脑子永远转不过这个弯
Something that you could never understand.
先生们动手吧
Gentlemen.
打开棺木
Open it.
我早就说了 没什么好怕的
You see? I told you there was nothing to be afraid of.
就是个
It's just…
小老太
…a little old lady.
准备把她运走
Prepare her for transport.
感觉哪里对不上
Something doesn't add up.
这些壁画里的她 根本不像暴君
She's not a monster in any of these paintings.
看上去是她自己要来岛上
It looks like she was taking herself here.
而不是被绑来的
Not being forced.
死亡女王令白昼变成了黑夜
The Death Queen turns day to night.
唯有她死亡 方能起死回生
She must die to bring back life.
起死回生
"Bring back life."
她只需用手轻轻一碰
Spreading death and destruction.
便可散布死亡与毁灭
with just the touch of her hand.
搬吧
Go on.
所有传说都有一定的现实基础
All myths have foundation in reality.
现实基础
…in reality.
其实我一个人 能拯救成千上万的人
Sacrificing one life is worth saving millions.
等等
Wait!
她是自愿牺牲自己的
She was sacrificing herself.
为了保护这个世界
She was protecting the world.
看见没有
See?
忽悠人的东西罢了
Smoke and mirrors.
好了 快点把她装起来
All right, let's bag her up. Come on.
古代人误以为这是邪术
They thought it was magic.
其实她是病毒携带者
She was a carrier.
她自身对这种病毒免疫
She was immune.
这是一种传染病
It's a disease.
圣三一想要的就是这个 有了这个 我就能回家了
This is what Trinity wants. This gets me home.
被带到外面的世界 必然引发大屠杀
If you take this out into the world, it's genocide.
我只需要拿着你身上的一小部分
I just need to take a very small piece of you.
快去抓住她
Go! Get her! Get her!
事已至此 理查德
Well, this is it, Richard.
我们离开这里便算大功告成
All we have to do is walk out of here.
你哪儿都别想去
You're not going anywhere.
得了 理查德
Come on, Richard.
想想你女儿
Think of your daughter.
出来
Come on.
- 爸爸 - 劳拉
- Dad. - Lara.
沃格尔跑了
Vogel's gone.
- 你得赶紧去追他 - 我们一起走
- You need to go after him. - Come on, let's go.
- 不 别过来 - 你在说什么
- No, stay back. Stay back. - What are you talking…
我已经不行了
I'm done for.
我被感染了
I'm infected.
不
No.
不可以碰我 别碰我
You can't touch me. Don't touch.
你必须阻止沃格尔 然后离开这里
You must stop Vogel and get the hell out of here.
我会把卑弥呼彻底埋葬
And I'll bury Himiko once and for all.
我刚刚才找到你
I've only just found you.
答应我 你会阻止他的 答应我
Promise me you'll stop him. Promise me!
一定还有别的办法
There must be another way.
劳拉
Lara.
你是个聪明姑娘 应该明白
You're a very, very bright young woman.
没有别的办法了
There's no other way.
我需要你
I need you.
你不需要 你能顶十个我
No, you don't. You're worth 10 of me.
你以前说你不相信魔法
You said you don't believe in magic.
难道这还不算吗 亲爱的
Well, what's this, my darling?
这些年在这里
All this time here…
我多希望看到你长大
I wished I could see you grow up.
不
No.
现在我看到了
And now I have.
这就是奇迹
It's a miracle.
打起精神 小不点
Chin up, sprout.
你还有使命要完成
There's jobs to do.
去吧 快去
Go on, go!
没时间了 劳拉
There's no time, Lara.
你快走
Go on, go!
爸爸爱你
Dad loves you.
我爱你
I love you.
你真要这么做吗 姑娘
Oh, you really wanna do this, little girl?
一起回家吧
Let's just go home.
你谁也救不了
You're not savin' anyone.
圣三一无处不在
Trinity is everywhere.
怎么样
Yeah?
我答应过他的
I made a promise.
不
No. No. No!
你死都别想出去
You're not getting out of here.
不
No! No!
见到理查德
When you see Richard,
记得替我问好
send him my regards.
你自己问候他吧
Send them yourself.
克劳馥家族可不是好惹的
You messed with the wrong family.
劳拉
Lara!
Lara?
好吧
Well…
至少我们还没死
We're not dead yet.
死不了
No shit.
沃格尔 巴特纳B5运输机呼叫 完毕
Vogel, Vogel, this is Patna Transport Bravo 5. Over.
沃格尔 收到吗 完毕
Vogel, Vogel, are you reading me? Over.
老大
Boss.
来送我们回去的吧
You're takin' us home, yeah?
（伦敦）
（劳拉·克劳馥）
正式死亡 像做梦一样
Officially gone. Like magic.
我觉得他没有离开
I don't think he has gone.
- 我在你身上看到了他的影子 - 谢谢 安娜
- I see so much of him in you. - Thanks, Ana.
真的
Really.
现在由你做主了 劳拉
You're in charge now, Lara.
这是我们公司的资产列表
This is a list of all our assets.
谢谢
Thank you.
我觉得公司的日常事务还是你来管理吧
No, I think you'd better stay on top of the day-to-day things, Ana.
好吧 任凭差遣
Well, as you wish.
董事会和生意
Boardrooms and business deals.
我不是那一类克劳馥家的人
I'm just not that kind of Croft.
想让我爸爸也和我一样
Neither was Dad, as it turns out.
上面的公司全都是我们的
Are all these companies owned by us?
是的
Yes.
（纪念理查德·克劳馥）
现在我知道他们是谁了
I know them by name now…
圣三一秘社
The Order of Trinity.
他们是一个好战的古老组织
An ancient militant organization.
寻求操纵自然力量的方法
that seeks control over the supernatural.
而统治全人类
in order to rule the fate of mankind.
（巴特纳 机密）
你的工作是什么
What kind of work do you do?
（巴特纳）
各种各样的事情 一切听我老板的
Oh, a mix of things. At the mercy of my employer.
上面的公司全都是我们的
Are all these companies owned by us?
（巴特纳有限公司）
你谁也救不了
You're not savin' anyone.
圣三一无处不在
Trinity is everywhere.
我知道这很难接受
I know it's difficult to accept.
但你真的必须来把那些文件签了
But you really must come in and sign those papers now.
（委托授权书）
我觉得公司的日常事务还是由你来管理吧
I think you'd better stay on top of the day-to-day things, Ana.
任凭差遣
As you wish.
我唯一能说话的对象就是
The only person that I get to talk to.
电话另一端的那些家伙
is on the other end of this phone.
你一定要明白
You must understand.
我们克劳馥家族肩负重任
We Crofts, we have responsibilities.
还有使命需要完成
Jobs to do.
《古墓丽影：源起之战》
又是你
Oh. You again.
我要赎回护身符
I came back for the amulet.
我还指望你忘了
Shame. I was hoping you'd forgotten.
那东西可值钱了
It's worth a bloody fortune.
我跟你说过 今天你撞大运
I did tell you it was your lucky day.
你还真说过
Yes, you did.
- 你又来了 艾伦 - 我没有
- At it again, are we, Alan? - I'm not at it.
你最好不要…
I don't know if you've noticed or not,
小心点
but, uh, you can't be too careful these days.
因为世界已经疯狂
because the world has gone bloody mad.
多谢提醒 艾伦
Yes, yes, thank you, Alan.
那把是HK USP 半自动 9毫米 加长弹夹
What you got there is a HK USP 9 mil. extended mag.
我的个人最爱
It's my personal favorite.
看来你喜欢
You like that?
没错
I do.
来两把
I'll take two.